<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>design system on Ivan's blog</title><link>https://raqystyle.github.io/tags/design-system/</link><description>Recent content in design system on Ivan's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raqystyle.github.io/tags/design-system/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Freedom of Web Components or Why UI Libraries Should Embrace Framework-Agnostic Solutions</title><link>https://raqystyle.github.io/blog/web-components-for-ui-lib/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raqystyle.github.io/blog/web-components-for-ui-lib/</guid><description>In the ever-evolving landscape of web development, the choice of tools and technologies can have a profound impact on the flexibility, scalability, and longevity of a code base. One critical decision that developers often face is whether to use a framework or embrace more framework-agnostic solutions like Web Components when building a UI library. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore why opting for Web Components can offer unparalleled advantages when it comes to ensuring flexibility and avoiding lock-in.</description></item><item><title>Design Systems as a layered cake</title><link>https://raqystyle.github.io/blog/layered-cake-ds/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://raqystyle.github.io/blog/layered-cake-ds/</guid><description>How do we structure a Design System? How do we make sure the architecture allows more people to contribute to it? What if there&amp;rsquo;s already a Design System in place, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work? During my time at Personio, I participated in the process of re-thinking the existing Design System. I noticed that dissecting the system into layers helped us answer some tricky questions. So, bear with me.
How it all starts In my experience, design systems always come after the main Product.</description></item></channel></rss>