<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>developer experience on Ivan's blog</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/tags/developer-experience/</link><description>Recent content in developer experience on Ivan's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/tags/developer-experience/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Model errors as data for better user and developer experience</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/models-errors-as-data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/models-errors-as-data/</guid><description>A great product experience is when the product works as expected in the scenario it was designed for, and communicates with users in a meaningful way. As developers, we cannot control how and where our product will be used, or the user input. But we have the tools to guard the flow from unexpected inputs. In this post, I want to give two pieces of advice for people working in the JS ecosystem on how to create better programs.</description></item><item><title>Simplifying Onboarding with Docker</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/docker-for-onboarding/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/docker-for-onboarding/</guid><description>Onboarding new team members can be a time-consuming and complicated process, especially when it comes to ensuring they have the right software and tools to do their jobs.
Traditional onboarding documentation can be unreliable and quickly outdated. In addition, IT professionals need to keep the device fleet up to date and free of vulnerabilities. Relying on others to maintain the documentation is often unsuccessful, as people tend to disregard updating documentation as a non-essential task.</description></item></channel></rss>