<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>JavaScript on Ivan's blog</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/tags/javascript/</link><description>Recent content in JavaScript on Ivan's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/tags/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>JavaScript is not viable any more</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/js-is-not-viable-anymore/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/js-is-not-viable-anymore/</guid><description>JavaScript is a dominant language for building web applications. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it for a very long time. However, in my opinion, it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t cut it any more. Luckily, there are some compelling alternatives.
JavaScript: A Dominant Yet Flawed Language JavaScript offers a quick and cheap solution for building web applications in the short term. However, in the long run, its design quirks and inherent flaws will work against its users.</description></item><item><title>TypeScript inherits all the flaws of JavaScript</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/js-and-ts-are-flawed-languages/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/js-and-ts-are-flawed-languages/</guid><description>Being a big proponent of TypeScript, I keep noticing that this language inherits all the flaws of JavaScript. However, it does not mean we have no choice.
The problem Consider a function that turns an object representing a URL into a string:
type UrlRecord = { protocol: string; host: string[]; } function urlToString(urlRecord: UrlRecord): string { const { protocol, host } = urlRecord; return `${protocol}://${host.join(&amp;#39;.&amp;#39;)}`; } This code snippet looks innocent and pretty solid.</description></item><item><title>Is JavaScript OOP or Functional?</title><link>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/is-js-oop-or-functional/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 12:33:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://ivan-demchenko.github.io/blog/is-js-oop-or-functional/</guid><description>A colleague of mine asked a good question: does TypeScript make JavaScript a better OOP language? To answer this question, I decided to compare OOP JavaScript to its opposite, Functional JavaScript.
TypeScript has become crazy popular. Many people bet on it as a magical language that will solve their JavaScript problems. Well, it won&amp;rsquo;t. As Kyle Simpson described in his upcoming book, the quirks of JavaScript don&amp;rsquo;t disappear. In my opinion, we should not attribute any superpowers to TS apart from just helping developers to feel more confident in the larger codebase.</description></item></channel></rss>